<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Random | ./home/davidsiaw]]></title>
  <link href="http://davidsiaw.github.io/blog/categories/random/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://davidsiaw.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2013-10-12T14:09:04+13:00</updated>
  <id>http://davidsiaw.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[davidsiaw]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Nice Visualization of a Cross Product]]></title>
    <link href="http://davidsiaw.github.io/blog/2012/11/18/nice-visualization-of-a-cross-product/"/>
    <updated>2012-11-18T00:00:00+13:00</updated>
    <id>http://davidsiaw.github.io/blog/2012/11/18/nice-visualization-of-a-cross-product</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.phy.syr.edu/courses/java-suite/crosspro.html">[This]</a> is a very nice Java applet that allows you to see what a cross product is. The applet shows A x B = C (i.e. C is the cross product of A and B) in 3 dimensions. You can drag A and B around to see the effects on C.</p>

<p>This UI is an example of very good interactivity. It makes it very easy for the user to see what happens and since its interactive, the feedback is instant and a little playing around with it gives the user an intuition of how cross products work (not how they are done).</p>

<p>Instead of a program where you enter numbers, dragging arrows around give you a much better view of whats going on, and allows the user to relate a real-life situation to it better too.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[GIS data for topography and shorelines and more]]></title>
    <link href="http://davidsiaw.github.io/blog/2009/03/20/gis-data-for-topography-and-shorelines-and-more/"/>
    <updated>2009-03-20T00:00:00+13:00</updated>
    <id>http://davidsiaw.github.io/blog/2009/03/20/gis-data-for-topography-and-shorelines-and-more</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&rsquo;ve <a href="http://www.ngdc.noaa.gov/mgg/topo/topo.html">found a site </a>recently that provides data for free on the world&rsquo;s shorelines and topography. They have got other datasets too that aren&rsquo;t as complete, but would probably be of interest to those of you who wish to do research on it. For me, when I look at data like this I get the itch to write programs that process and present it. I might just do that eventually. <em>keeps a note to self</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Windows blues]]></title>
    <link href="http://davidsiaw.github.io/blog/2008/10/06/windows-blues/"/>
    <updated>2008-10-06T00:00:00+13:00</updated>
    <id>http://davidsiaw.github.io/blog/2008/10/06/windows-blues</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>After losing a few games of command and conquer and the computer blue screening when I&rsquo;m just about to win, I am thoroughly convinced that contrary to their ads, Microsoft has never intended to make life easy for anyone. I swear by my keyboard I will make an OS that is actually reliable and usable by everyone someday. UURGH!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Shaders, where math meets art]]></title>
    <link href="http://davidsiaw.github.io/blog/2008/09/17/shaders-where-math-meets-art/"/>
    <updated>2008-09-17T00:00:00+12:00</updated>
    <id>http://davidsiaw.github.io/blog/2008/09/17/shaders-where-math-meets-art</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/images/blogimages/db3.jpg"></p>

<p>Since playing with shaders is so much fun, lets have a little fun looking at what happens when you take an old game, and breathe some new life into it using a crazily reprogrammed pipeline:</p>

<object width="425" height="344"><param name="movie" value="http://www.youtube.com/v/bfy6sMgKDwA&hl=en&fs=1"></param><param name="allowFullScreen" value="true"></param><embed src="http://www.youtube.com/v/bfy6sMgKDwA&hl=en&fs=1" type="application/x-shockwave-flash" allowfullscreen="true" width="425" height="344"></embed></object>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Reset]]></title>
    <link href="http://davidsiaw.github.io/blog/2008/08/23/reset/"/>
    <updated>2008-08-23T00:00:00+12:00</updated>
    <id>http://davidsiaw.github.io/blog/2008/08/23/reset</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I never seem to be satisfied with any of the sites I made, so I made myself swear that this is the last time I&rsquo;m going to replace the Labs site. The last one was a bit of a joke anyway. If you ever have a choice, Drupal 6 isn&rsquo;t exactly a good CMS for building production sites, unless you have got plenty of in-house expertise. When you have to spend a whole day messing around with it to get it to let you post just one blog post, perhaps it just isn&rsquo;t built to write posts.</p>

<p>So the difference is, yes I have moved down to the Wordpress side to avoid the grief that comes with Drupal. I have decided that hacking something that works well is easier that hacking something that is borked. So I have decided that I will hack this. Woot. Now back to coding.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
