<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: math | ./home/davidsiaw]]></title>
  <link href="http://davidsiaw.github.io/blog/categories/math/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://davidsiaw.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2019-08-17T15:32:24+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://davidsiaw.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[davidsiaw]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Rotating Integrals]]></title>
    <link href="http://davidsiaw.github.io/blog/2015/12/22/rotating-integrals/"/>
    <updated>2015-12-22T01:11:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://davidsiaw.github.io/blog/2015/12/22/rotating-integrals</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>This post assumes you know some trigonometry and can do some integral calculus on it.</em></p>

<p>My little brother in college complained about sines and cosines in an indefinite integral today. Specifically, an integration that he was annoyed with was:</p>

<p>\[\int{x^3\,sin(x)\,dx}\]</p>

<p>It sounded like a whine at first but upon closer inspection, his complaints are not unwarranted. This is indeed a troublesome kind of indefinite integral. There is a trick to doing it quickly, but let us try and perform this particular integration normally first:</p>

<p>Since this is integration of the product of two functions, we perform integration by parts.</p>

<p>\[\int{u\,dv} = uv\, - \int{v\,du}\]</p>

<p>I choose \(u = x^3\) and \(dv = sin(x)\,dx\) mostly to avoid having to integrate the \(x^3\) and have fractions mess up my working.</p>

<p>This results in:</p>

<p>\[
\begin{aligned}
 u &amp; = x^3 \cr
 du &amp; = 3x^2\,dx \cr
 dv &amp; = sin(x)\,dx \cr
 v &amp; = -cos(x)
\end{aligned}
\]</p>

<p>Hence:</p>

<p>\[
\begin{aligned}
 \int{u\,dv} &amp; = uv\, - \int{v\,du} \cr
 &amp; = -x^3\,cos(x)\, - \int{–3x^2 cos(x)\,dx} \cr
 &amp; = -x^3\,cos(x) + \int{3x^2 cos(x)\,dx}
\end{aligned}
\]</p>

<p>We seem to have ended up with another integral to solve: \(\int{cos(x)(3x^2)\,dx}\), so we shall proceed to solve it.</p>

<p>\[
\begin{array}{cc}
 \begin{aligned}
  \int{u\,dv} &amp; = uv\, - \int{v\,du} \cr
  \int{3x^2 cos(x)\,dx} &amp; = 3x^2 sin(x)\, - \int{6x\,sin(x)\,dx}
 \end{aligned} &amp;
 \begin{aligned}
  u &amp; = 3x^2 \cr
  du &amp; = 6x\,dx \cr
  dv &amp; = cos(x)\,dx \cr
  v &amp; = sin(x)
 \end{aligned}
\end{array}
\]</p>

<p>How vexing. We have yet another integral to solve. Let us proceed anyway.</p>

<p>\[
\begin{array}{cc}
 \begin{aligned}
  \int{u\,dv} &amp; = uv\, - \int{v\,du} \cr
  \int{6x\,sin(x)\,dx} &amp; = -6x\,cos(x)\, - \int{-6\,cos(x)\,dx} \cr
  \int{6x\,sin(x)\,dx} &amp; = -6x\,cos(x) + \int{6\,cos(x)\,dx}
 \end{aligned} &amp;
 \begin{aligned}
  u &amp; = 6x \cr
  du &amp; = 6\,dx \cr
  dv &amp; = sin(x)\,dx \cr
  v &amp; = -cos(x)
 \end{aligned}
\end{array}
\]</p>

<p>Once again, we have to solve another integral. This one seems to be the last though, because the x term has withered away into oblivion, it becomes a trivial integral.</p>

<p>\[
\begin{aligned}
 \int{6x\,sin(x)\,dx} &amp; = -6x\,cos(x) + \int{6\,cos(x)\,dx} \cr
 &amp; = -6x\,cos(x) + 6\int{cos(x)\,dx} \cr
 &amp; = -6x\,cos(x) + 6\,sin(x)
\end{aligned}
\]</p>

<p>Bringing it all together, we have:</p>

<p>\[
\begin{aligned}
 \int{x^3\,sin(x)\,dx} &amp; = -x^3\,cos(x) + \int{3x^2 cos(x)\,dx} \cr
 &amp; = -x^3\,cos(x) + 3x^2 sin(x)\, - \int{6x\,sin(x)\,dx} \cr
 &amp; = -x^3\,cos(x) + 3x^2 sin(x)\, - [-6x\,cos(x) + \int{6\,cos(x)\,dx}] \cr
 &amp; = -x^3\,cos(x) + 3x^2 sin(x)\, - [-6x\,cos(x) + 6\,sin(x)] \cr
 &amp; = -x^3\,cos(x) + 3x^2 sin(x)\, + 6x\,cos(x) - 6\,sin(x)
\end{aligned}
\]</p>

<p>Phew! Basically due to the fact that you have to integrate by parts as many times as the <em>power of x</em>, the amount of integration you have to do increases proportionally to x&rsquo;s power, making it troublesome.</p>

<h2>A Closer Look</h2>

<p>However, if you have been following the working closely, you will notice that all we are really doing when we integrate by parts is performing a derivative of both parts over and over again. Notice how the \(sin(x)\) term keeps flipping between \(sin(x)\) and \(cos(x)\).</p>

<p>Better yet, if you differentiate \(sin(x)\) 4 times, the entire thing rotates back to \(sin(x)\) again. Since we integrated \(sin(x)\) 4 times in this example, that is exactly what happened. I call this kind of integral a <strong>Rotating Integral</strong> because the trigonometric term constantly rotates between the four combinations of negative and positive, \(sin(x)\) and \(cos(x)\).</p>

<p>Notice also that the \(u\) term we chose right at the beginning was differentiated at every step until it became a constant:</p>

<p>\[x^3\,\rightarrow\,3x^2\,\rightarrow\,6x\,\rightarrow\,6\]</p>

<p>If we factorize the result, we get the following:</p>

<p>\[
 -x^3\,cos(x) + 3x^2 sin(x)\, + 6x\,cos(x) - 6\,sin(x) = (-x^3 + 6x)\,cos(x) + (3x^2 - 6)\,sin(x)
\]</p>

<p>Notice how there is a negative term in both the \(sin(x)\) and \(cos(x)\) groups. Since the starting \(u\) we chose was positive, we can see the \(sin(x)\) go through</p>

<p>\[-cos(x)\,\rightarrow\,-sin(x)\,\rightarrow\,cos(x)\,\rightarrow\,sin(x)\]</p>

<p>We can see a pattern of repeating derivatives distributed among the \(sin(x)\) and \(cos(x)\) groups. If we recognize that</p>

<p>\[
\begin{array}{cc}
 x^3 &amp;\rightarrow\,3x^2 &amp;\rightarrow\,6x &amp;\rightarrow\,6 \cr
 f &amp;\rightarrow\,f^\prime &amp;\rightarrow\,f^{\prime \prime} &amp;\rightarrow\,f^{\prime \prime \prime} \cr
\end{array}
\]</p>

<p>And from our rearranged result,</p>

<p>\[
(-f + f^{\prime \prime})\,cos(x) + (f^\prime - f^{\prime \prime \prime})\,sin(x)
\]</p>

<p>This peaked my interest, and I decided to check the results of other powers of x:</p>

<p>\[
\begin{array}{cc}
3 &amp; (-x^3 + 6x)\,cos(x) &amp; + (3x^2 - 6)\,sin(x) \cr
4 &amp; (-x^4 + 12x^2 - 24)\,cos(x) &amp; + (4x^3 - 24x)\,sin(x) \cr
5 &amp; (-x^5 + 20x^3 - 120x)\,cos(x) &amp; + (5x^4 - 60x^2 + 120)\,sin(x) \cr
6 &amp; (-x^6 + 30x^4 - 360x^2 + 720)\,cos(x) &amp; + (6x^5 - 120x^3 + 720x)\,sin(x) \cr
7 &amp; (-x^7 + 42x^5 - 840x^3 + 5040x)\,cos(x) &amp; + (7x^6 - 210x^4 + 2520x^2 - 5040)\,sin(x)
\end{array}
\]</p>

<h2>The Solution!</h2>

<p>After doing some more wolframming, I found that we have a general solution of:</p>

<p>\[
\int{f\,sin(x)\,dx} = (- f + f^{\prime \prime} - f^{\prime \prime \prime \prime} + \cdots - f^{\prime2n})\,cos(x) + (f^{\prime} - f^{\prime \prime \prime} + f^{\prime \prime \prime \prime \prime} - \cdots + f^{\prime2n+1})\,sin(x)
\]</p>

<p>Where odd numbered differentials are on the \(sin(x)\) group and even numbered differentials are on the \(cos(x)\) group, and each differential alternates between negative and positive signs. The \(sin(x)\) group starts with a positive sign while the \(cos(x)\) starts with a negative sign.</p>

<p>Of course, the same rule slightly modified works for the \(cos(x)\) form:</p>

<p>\[
\int{f\,cos(x)\,dx} = (f - f^{\prime \prime} + f^{\prime \prime \prime \prime} - \cdots + f^{\prime2n})\,sin(x) + (f^{\prime} - f^{\prime \prime \prime} + f^{\prime \prime \prime \prime \prime} - \cdots + f^{\prime2n+1})\,cos(x)
\]</p>

<p>Note that this only works if \(f\) eventually derives into 0, and if the trigonometric function is \(sin(x)\) or \(cos(x)\). Otherwise you will need another method of finding the solution.</p>

<h2>Weird Application</h2>

<p>With this we can try and verify that what I said was true by trying to use it on a very special function that does not change even when under differentiation: \(e^x\). Even though I said this only works if it eventually derives to zero, let us try anyway:</p>

<p>So for this let us try the following function:</p>

<p>\[\int{e^x\,sin(x)\,dx}\]</p>

<p>This should give us</p>

<p>\[
\begin{align}
 \int{e^x\,sin(x)\,dx} &amp; = (- e^x + e^x - e^x + \cdots)\,cos(x) + (e^x - e^x + e^x - \cdots)\,sin(x) &amp; \cr
  &amp; = (- e^x + e^x - e^x + \cdots)\,cos(x) - (-e^x + e^x - e^x + \cdots)\,sin(x) &amp; \text{If we flip the sign}\cr
  &amp; = (- e^x + e^x - e^x + \cdots)(cos(x) - sin(x)) &amp; \text{Hence} \cr
  &amp; = (-1+1-1+\cdots)(e^x)(cos(x) - sin(x)) &amp;
\end{align}
\]</p>

<p>We are left with a strange, almost nonsensical looking sum that looks like it should evaluate to zero, but does it?</p>

<p>\[
\begin{align}
 S &amp; = -1+1-1+1-1+1\cdots \cr
 S &amp; = -1-S \cr
 2S &amp; = -1 \cr
 S &amp; = -\frac{1}{2} \cr
\end{align}
\]</p>

<p>Oh so that infinite sum actually evaluates to \(-\frac{1}{2}\). This may seem dubious but proving that is outside the scope of this post. (Lots of people have done it anyway.) This just means that our thing above should look like this:</p>

<p>\[
\begin{align}
 \int{e^x\,sin(x)\,dx}&amp; = (-1+1-1+\cdots)(e^x)(cos(x) - sin(x)) \cr
 &amp; = -\frac{1}{2}(e^x)(cos(x) - sin(x)) \cr
 &amp; = \frac{1}{2}(e^x)(sin(x)-cos(x)) \cr
\end{align}
\]</p>

<p>But is this correct? We must try and check again that we did not just stumble on nonsense.</p>

<h2>Verifying again</h2>

<p>To verify, let us perform it again with good ol' integration by parts.</p>

<p>\[\int{e^x\,sin(x)\,dx}\]</p>

<p>\[
\begin{array}{cc}
 \begin{aligned}
  \int{u\,dv} &amp; = uv\, - \int{v\,du} \cr
  \int{sin(x)(e^x)\,dx} &amp; =  sin(x)(e^x)\, - \int{e^x\,cos(x)\,dx}
 \end{aligned} &amp;
 \begin{aligned}
  u &amp; = sin(x) \cr
  du &amp; = cos(x)\,dx \cr
  dv &amp; = e^x\,dx \cr
  v &amp; = e^x
 \end{aligned}
\end{array}
\]</p>

<p>We have to do this integration again for \(cos(x)\), so let us do so.</p>

<p>\[
\begin{array}{cc}
 \begin{aligned}
  \int{u\,dv} &amp; = uv\, - \int{v\,du} \cr
  \int{e^x\,cos(x)\,dx} &amp; =  cos(x)(e^x)\, + \int{e^x\,sin(x)\,dx}
 \end{aligned} &amp;
 \begin{aligned}
  u &amp; = cos(x) \cr
  du &amp; = -sin(x)\,dx \cr
  dv &amp; = e^x\,dx \cr
  v &amp; = e^x
 \end{aligned}
\end{array}
\]</p>

<p>Substituting back, we get:</p>

<p>\[
\begin{aligned}
 \int{sin(x)(e^x)\,dx} &amp; = sin(x)(e^x)\, - \int{e^x\,cos(x)\,dx} \cr
 &amp; = sin(x)(e^x)\, - cos(x)(e^x)\, - \int{e^x\,sin(x)\,dx} \cr
 2\int{sin(x)(e^x)\,dx} &amp; = sin(x)(e^x)\, - cos(x)(e^x) \cr
 \int{sin(x)(e^x)\,dx} &amp; = \frac{1}{2}(e^x)(sin(x)-cos(x))
\end{aligned}
\]</p>

<p>Which is the same result we got before, proving that we didn&rsquo;t screw up.</p>

<p>With this, you can find the indefinite integral of expressions of this form by simply differentiating the non-trigonometric side. You can also use identities, factorizations and other ways to rearrange an expression into this form to use this technique to integrate this otherwise troublesome class of <strong>Rotating Integrals</strong>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Finding Square Roots]]></title>
    <link href="http://davidsiaw.github.io/blog/2015/06/12/finding-square-roots/"/>
    <updated>2015-06-12T01:36:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://davidsiaw.github.io/blog/2015/06/12/finding-square-roots</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Most of us has at some point in our lives used the <code>Math.sqrt()</code> function. We would even know that \(\sqrt{2} = 1.414\ldots\). However, we never really give how it is implemented a second thought. Thus is the power of a tight abstraction. For those of us who lived in the age of calculators, finding square roots has always been a source of mystery. For me during my teenage years, calculating a square root has really just been about looking up a numeric table.</p>

<p><img src="/images/log8.jpg" alt="Table of Square Roots" /></p>

<p>Obviously this very simple problem would have been solved close to the beginnings of civilization, and blazingly fast methods must already exist. But for sake of exploration, let us examine how we would implement a square root function should we need to.</p>

<p>\[\sqrt{-n} = \sqrt{-1} \sqrt{n}\]</p>

<p>Since square roots of negative numbers are really just square roots of positive numbers times the square root of a negative number, let us focus our efforts on finding just the square roots of positive real numbers.</p>

<p><img src="/images/square.png" alt="y=x^2" /></p>

<p>One way to find a square root is by looking at this graph of \(y=x^2\). Simply drawing a horizontal line from the y-axis from whose square root we desire to the graph line, and then find the intersect on the x-axis. So say we want \(\sqrt{30}\).</p>

<p><img src="/images/sqrt30.png" alt="find sqrt 30" /></p>

<p>We simply draw a line from the y-axis at 30 to the graph and find that it is located somewhere between 5.4 and 5.6 along the x-axis, but closer to 5.4. This makes sense. A quick glance at <a href="https://www.google.co.jp/webhp?sourceid=chrome-instant&amp;ion=1&amp;espv=2&amp;ie=UTF-8#q=sqrt(30">google</a>) shows \(\sqrt{30} = 5.4772255\)</p>

<p><img src="/images/binaryguessing.png" alt="find sqrt 30" /></p>

<p>This in-betweenness tells us something about square roots. Besides the nice square roots, the ugly ones don&rsquo;t seem to have any end to their decimals. Hence, they are always in between two numbers that we know. This means that we can keep making educated guesses about where the square root is until we get close enough.</p>

<p>\[0 &lt; \sqrt{30} &lt; 30\]</p>

<p>Let&rsquo;s apply this knowledge first and do the calculation by hand for the number 30 since we know its answer so we can verify that our method is correct.</p>

<p>First of all, we must figure out where the root is. Obviously, it would be less than 30, since you need to multiply it by itself to get 30. Its also more than zero, because as mentioned earlier, you will always end up with a positive number.</p>

<p>\[\sqrt{30} \approx 15?\]</p>

<p>The number most in between of 0 and 30 is 15. But is this the number? The only way to check is by squaring 15.</p>

<p>\[15^2 = 225\]</p>

<p>Nope. Not even close. 225 is waaay too big. But this tells us something: the root cannot be bigger than 15 because if it was, we would get an even bigger square than 30, so we must look to the left of 15. This means our upper bound is now 15 instead of 30.</p>

<p>\[0 &lt; \sqrt{30} &lt; 15\]</p>

<p>The number in the middle this time is 7.5. Is this our number?</p>

<p>\[7.5^2 = 56.25\]</p>

<p>Still too big. This means our root must be smaller than 7.5, but still bigger than zero.</p>

<p>\[0 &lt; \sqrt{30} &lt; 7.5\]</p>

<p>The number in the middle of 7.5 is 3.75. Perhaps this is our number?</p>

<p>\[3.75^2 = 14.0625\]</p>

<p>It seems the square of 3.75 is smaller than 30! This means that that the root must be bigger than 3.75 since if the number is smaller, we get an even smaller square, we must be getting close.</p>

<p>\[3.75 &lt; \sqrt{30} &lt; 7.5\]</p>

<p>Now we must find out what number is in the middle. Well, from our geometry class we know that the average of two numbers is the middle number, so \(\frac{3.75 + 7.5}{2} = 5.625\). We simply need to square this number to check now.</p>

<p>\[5.625^2 = 31.640625\]</p>

<p>It seems we have gotten a lot closer now that we moved the lower bound up. Our guess of 5.625 seems really close to the answer now. But because its square is bigger than 30, we know the root must be smaller than 5.625, so:</p>

<p>\[3.75 &lt; \sqrt{30} &lt; 5.625\]</p>

<p>The middle number of this is then 4.6875.</p>

<p>\[4.6875^2 = 21.972656\]</p>

<p>That&rsquo;s really far away. This can&rsquo;t be the answer, but lets keep looking. Since its square is smaller than 30, we change the lower bound to this.</p>

<p>\[4.6875 &lt; \sqrt{30} &lt; 5.625\]</p>

<p>This time, the middle number is 5.15625.</p>

<p>\[5.15625^2 = 26.586914\]</p>

<p>We are getting closer again, but this is smaller than 30, so our lower bound should be changed.</p>

<p>\[5.15625 &lt; \sqrt{30} &lt; 5.625\]</p>

<p>I know, it starts to get frustrating at this point since we seem to be crawling, but lets stay on for another two rounds. The number in the middle is 5.390625</p>

<p>\[5.390625^2 = 29.058838\]</p>

<p>Our result now is very very close to 30. It is smaller, so the lower bound should be changed.</p>

<p>\[5.390625 &lt; \sqrt{30} &lt; 5.625\]</p>

<p>The middle number is now 5.507812. That means the square is&hellip;</p>

<p>\[5.507812^2 = 30.336\]</p>

<p>Okay! We are pretty close, but the important thing is we know it will eventually arrive at the answer because we kept getting closer to the answer as we went. Now, we know computers do things faster than we do so let us write some code!</p>

<p>So first of all, we want to have our initial guess. The number to be rooted is 30.</p>

<pre><code class="c++">double number = 30;

double upperBound = number;
double lowerBound = 0;
</code></pre>

<p>Then, we write down what we did in every iteration.</p>

<pre><code class="c++">// We try and figure out if the middle number is the correct root
double rootGuess = (upperBound + lowerBound) / 2;
double rootGuessSquared = rootGuess * rootGuess;

if (rootGuessSquared &gt; number)
{
    // if the square of our guess is bigger than the number, that means the root is too big.
    // so the root cannot be bigger than our current guess
    upperBound = rootGuess;
}
else
{
    // otherwise, the root cannot be smaller than our current guess.
    lowerBound = rootGuess;
}
</code></pre>

<p>Next, we tell the computer to do it over and over again until the square of our guess is the number itself, so we wrap that in a loop.</p>

<pre><code class="c++">double rootGuess = 0;
do
{
    // We try and figure out if the middle number is the correct root
    rootGuess = (upperBound + lowerBound) / 2;
    double rootGuessSquared = rootGuess * rootGuess;

    if (rootGuessSquared &gt; number)
    {
        // if the square of our guess is bigger than the number, that means the root is too big.
        // so the root cannot be bigger than our current guess
        upperBound = rootGuess;
    }
    else
    {
        // otherwise, the root cannot be smaller than our current guess.
        lowerBound = rootGuess;
    }

} while(rootGuess * rootGuess != number);
</code></pre>

<p>Great, that seems simple enough. Let&rsquo;s put it all together.</p>

<pre><code class="c++">double number = 30;

double upperBound = number;
double lowerBound = 0;

double rootGuess = 0;
do
{
    // We try and figure out if the middle number is the correct root
    rootGuess = (upperBound + lowerBound) / 2;
    double rootGuessSquared = rootGuess * rootGuess;

    if (rootGuessSquared &gt; number)
    {
        // if the square of our guess is bigger than the number, that means the root is too big.
        // so the root cannot be bigger than our current guess
        upperBound = rootGuess;
    }
    else
    {
        // otherwise, the root cannot be smaller than our current guess.
        lowerBound = rootGuess;
    }

    printf("%lf &lt; sqrt(30) &lt; %lf guess=%lf rootGuessSquared=%lf\n", upperBound, lowerBound, rootGuess, rootGuessSquared);

} while(rootGuess * rootGuess != number);

printf("result = %lf\n", rootGuess);
</code></pre>

<p>Notice I put in a printf to check the bounds as it runs. This makes it more interesting and actually shows us what&rsquo;s going on. Lets run it now.</p>

<pre><code>15.000000 &lt; sqrt(30) &lt; 0.000000 guess=15.000000 rootGuessSquared=225.000000
7.500000 &lt; sqrt(30) &lt; 0.000000 guess=7.500000 rootGuessSquared=56.250000
7.500000 &lt; sqrt(30) &lt; 3.750000 guess=3.750000 rootGuessSquared=14.062500
5.625000 &lt; sqrt(30) &lt; 3.750000 guess=5.625000 rootGuessSquared=31.640625
5.625000 &lt; sqrt(30) &lt; 4.687500 guess=4.687500 rootGuessSquared=21.972656
5.625000 &lt; sqrt(30) &lt; 5.156250 guess=5.156250 rootGuessSquared=26.586914
5.625000 &lt; sqrt(30) &lt; 5.390625 guess=5.390625 rootGuessSquared=29.058838
5.507812 &lt; sqrt(30) &lt; 5.390625 guess=5.507812 rootGuessSquared=30.335999
5.507812 &lt; sqrt(30) &lt; 5.449219 guess=5.449219 rootGuessSquared=29.693985
5.478516 &lt; sqrt(30) &lt; 5.449219 guess=5.478516 rootGuessSquared=30.014133
5.478516 &lt; sqrt(30) &lt; 5.463867 guess=5.463867 rootGuessSquared=29.853845
5.478516 &lt; sqrt(30) &lt; 5.471191 guess=5.471191 rootGuessSquared=29.933935
5.478516 &lt; sqrt(30) &lt; 5.474854 guess=5.474854 rootGuessSquared=29.974021
5.478516 &lt; sqrt(30) &lt; 5.476685 guess=5.476685 rootGuessSquared=29.994074
5.477600 &lt; sqrt(30) &lt; 5.476685 guess=5.477600 rootGuessSquared=30.004103
5.477600 &lt; sqrt(30) &lt; 5.477142 guess=5.477142 rootGuessSquared=29.999088
5.477371 &lt; sqrt(30) &lt; 5.477142 guess=5.477371 rootGuessSquared=30.001595
5.477257 &lt; sqrt(30) &lt; 5.477142 guess=5.477257 rootGuessSquared=30.000342
5.477257 &lt; sqrt(30) &lt; 5.477200 guess=5.477200 rootGuessSquared=29.999715
5.477228 &lt; sqrt(30) &lt; 5.477200 guess=5.477228 rootGuessSquared=30.000028
5.477228 &lt; sqrt(30) &lt; 5.477214 guess=5.477214 rootGuessSquared=29.999872
5.477228 &lt; sqrt(30) &lt; 5.477221 guess=5.477221 rootGuessSquared=29.999950
5.477228 &lt; sqrt(30) &lt; 5.477225 guess=5.477225 rootGuessSquared=29.999989
5.477226 &lt; sqrt(30) &lt; 5.477225 guess=5.477226 rootGuessSquared=30.000009
5.477226 &lt; sqrt(30) &lt; 5.477225 guess=5.477225 rootGuessSquared=29.999999
5.477226 &lt; sqrt(30) &lt; 5.477225 guess=5.477226 rootGuessSquared=30.000004
5.477226 &lt; sqrt(30) &lt; 5.477225 guess=5.477226 rootGuessSquared=30.000001
5.477226 &lt; sqrt(30) &lt; 5.477225 guess=5.477226 rootGuessSquared=30.000000
5.477226 &lt; sqrt(30) &lt; 5.477226 guess=5.477226 rootGuessSquared=30.000000
5.477226 &lt; sqrt(30) &lt; 5.477226 guess=5.477226 rootGuessSquared=30.000000
5.477226 &lt; sqrt(30) &lt; 5.477226 guess=5.477226 rootGuessSquared=30.000000
5.477226 &lt; sqrt(30) &lt; 5.477226 guess=5.477226 rootGuessSquared=30.000000
5.477226 &lt; sqrt(30) &lt; 5.477226 guess=5.477226 rootGuessSquared=30.000000
5.477226 &lt; sqrt(30) &lt; 5.477226 guess=5.477226 rootGuessSquared=30.000000
5.477226 &lt; sqrt(30) &lt; 5.477226 guess=5.477226 rootGuessSquared=30.000000
5.477226 &lt; sqrt(30) &lt; 5.477226 guess=5.477226 rootGuessSquared=30.000000
5.477226 &lt; sqrt(30) &lt; 5.477226 guess=5.477226 rootGuessSquared=30.000000
5.477226 &lt; sqrt(30) &lt; 5.477226 guess=5.477226 rootGuessSquared=30.000000
5.477226 &lt; sqrt(30) &lt; 5.477226 guess=5.477226 rootGuessSquared=30.000000
5.477226 &lt; sqrt(30) &lt; 5.477226 guess=5.477226 rootGuessSquared=30.000000
5.477226 &lt; sqrt(30) &lt; 5.477226 guess=5.477226 rootGuessSquared=30.000000
5.477226 &lt; sqrt(30) &lt; 5.477226 guess=5.477226 rootGuessSquared=30.000000
5.477226 &lt; sqrt(30) &lt; 5.477226 guess=5.477226 rootGuessSquared=30.000000
5.477226 &lt; sqrt(30) &lt; 5.477226 guess=5.477226 rootGuessSquared=30.000000
5.477226 &lt; sqrt(30) &lt; 5.477226 guess=5.477226 rootGuessSquared=30.000000
5.477226 &lt; sqrt(30) &lt; 5.477226 guess=5.477226 rootGuessSquared=30.000000
5.477226 &lt; sqrt(30) &lt; 5.477226 guess=5.477226 rootGuessSquared=30.000000
5.477226 &lt; sqrt(30) &lt; 5.477226 guess=5.477226 rootGuessSquared=30.000000
5.477226 &lt; sqrt(30) &lt; 5.477226 guess=5.477226 rootGuessSquared=30.000000
5.477226 &lt; sqrt(30) &lt; 5.477226 guess=5.477226 rootGuessSquared=30.000000
5.477226 &lt; sqrt(30) &lt; 5.477226 guess=5.477226 rootGuessSquared=30.000000
5.477226 &lt; sqrt(30) &lt; 5.477226 guess=5.477226 rootGuessSquared=30.000000
5.477226 &lt; sqrt(30) &lt; 5.477226 guess=5.477226 rootGuessSquared=30.000000
5.477226 &lt; sqrt(30) &lt; 5.477226 guess=5.477226 rootGuessSquared=30.000000
5.477226 &lt; sqrt(30) &lt; 5.477226 guess=5.477226 rootGuessSquared=30.000000
result = 5.477226
</code></pre>

<p>After all that spam, now we can see that the result is the square root of 30, since we know 5.477226 is the square root of 30.</p>

<p>This method of calculating square roots is called the Bisection method, also known as a binary search. Its not very efficient as you can see, and takes a long time to converge.</p>

<p>Now we know what it takes to find a square root! Now you can simply try it with a bunch of numbers and get the right answer. You can also compare the answer with the actual sqrt() function provided by the standard library.</p>

<p>It is also interesting to note that you can use this method to get cube roots, quartic roots and quintic roots too.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
